Guide to the Ghana Collection
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Ghana collection
1877-2012
MS 1519
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
15.28
(16 boxes)
The collection consists of correspondence, printed material, writings, photographs, ephemera, and posters relating to the history of the Gold Coast (now known as Ghana) and the current political, economic, and social conditions.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Transferred from the African Collection Curator.
Associated Materials
African Collection, MS 605; African Postcard Collection, MS 1575, Pamphlet Collection, MS 1351. Manuscripts and Archives, Yale University Library.
Arrangement
The material in the original accession is arranged chronologically, with photographs last. Additions to the collection may vary in arrangement.
Scope and Contents
The collection consists of correspondence, printed material, writings, photographs, ephemera, and posters relating to the history of the Gold Coast (now known as Ghana) and the current political, economic, and social conditions.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Original audiovisual materials, as well as preservation and duplicating masters, may not be played. Researchers must consult use copies, or if none exist must pay for a use copy, which is retained by the repository. Researchers wishing to obtain an additional copy of non-commercially produced items for their personal use should consult the ordering reproductions information on the Manuscripts and Archives web site.
Railroads -- Ghana; Ghana -- Description and travel; Ghana -- Economic conditions; Ghana -- History; Ghana -- Politics and government; Ghana -- Social conditions; Photographs -- Ghana; Posters -- Ghana; Fenton, Frederick A.; Kufuor, John Agyekum, 1938-; Electoral Commission of Ghana
- Inventory
  General
  "Gold Coast Sponsors Group of the Ghana Congress Party: documents; letters; reports; lists of autographs, 1952-1954" (formerly box 1, folder 12) is missing from the collection as of 2014.
  - Gold Coast Constabulary: papers relating to Assistant Inspector Frederick A. Fenton of the White Volta District, 1899-1903 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Gold Coast Government Railways: first class free pass issued to Lieutenant W. G. Kettle; map of the railway; photographs taken by Kettle during survey of proposed new line from Kumasi to Accra, 1913 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Education: school bulletins, pamphlets, printed material, 1930-1992 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Periodicals: magazines; popular journals, 1934-1993 (Box 1, Folder 4 - 5)
  - The Gold Coast Handbook: produced in England by the authority of the publishers, the Gold Coast Government, 1937 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Northern Territories Welfare Committee: documents, 1944 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - General information pamphlets; brochures; booklets, 1946-1992, undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Letters and photographs sent by Sonja and Janje Wyllie to Helen and Adelbert Poka-Pivny regarding their stay in Ghana and the birth of their son, Janik, 1949-1951 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Government documents: speeches; journals; releases, 1950-1965 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Elections: printed material, 1951-1987 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Castles and forts of the Gold Coast: calendar, 1956 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Independence celebration: programs, essays, 1957 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Industrial Development Corporation: survey report, 1957 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Obituaries; funeral orations of political and tribal figures, 1959, 1990 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - "Tradition and Change - Problems of Progress," by Russell Warren Howe, 1959 March (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Political organizations: journals; newsletters; printed material, 1965-1992, undated (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - State Shipping Corporation: reports on the Black Star Line, 1966 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Newspapers, 1985-1991 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Royal Air Force during World War II: photograph album and loose photographs, 1943 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Village life: photographs by Robert S. Boyd, 1982 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Photograph album of Harold J. Cox, undated (Box 2, Folder 23)
- Additional Material, Accession 1995-M-051
  General note
  Also includes Accession 1995-M-054
  - West African Cocoa, Anglo-Guinea Produce Co., Ltd., 1925 (Box 1)
  - "Rebuilding the National Economy": broadcast speech of the National Liberation Council, 1966 March 2 (Box 1)
- Additional Material, Accession 1995-M-176
  - Additional printed materials, 1877-1927, 1950, 1962, 1989-1995, undated (Box 1)
- Additional Material, Accession 2006-M-059
  Scope and Contents
  This material is arranged alphabetically by title and/or personal name. Photographs and a drawing are at the end of the accession.
  - The African Spectator, vol. 2, no. 10, 1963 March 9 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - City News, vol.1, no. 6, 1978 May, June (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - "Code of Conduct for Political Parties in Ghana", 2000 May 18 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - The Echo, vol. LXIII, no. 195, 1987 May 31 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - "Fighting Words, Proverbs in Asafo Flags of Ghana," program for an exhibit at The Textile Museum, Washington, D.C., 2001 May 25-August 12 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - "Firaw, Volta Hall Magazine", 1987 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Funtime, undated (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - GBC Radio and TV Times, vol. 21, no. 2, 1984 July-September (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Ghana Confidential, vol. 2, no. 3, 1974 Oct, November (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - "Ghana News Bulletin," vol. 3, no. 11, 1975 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Ghana Observer, vol. 1, no. 7, [1984] (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - The Ghanaian, no. 1, 1958 July (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - GJA (Ghana Journalists Association) Guidelines on Election Coverage, undated (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Institute of Current World Affairs, reports by Peter Bird Martin on the economy of Ghana, 1980 June 30, 1981 April 27, 30 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Labour, Ghana Trade Union Congress (TUC ), vol. 1, nos. 1, 4, 1960 Jul, October (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Nkrumah, Dr. Kwame (Osagyefo), president of the Republic of Ghana
    - "The Volta River Project", 1961 February 21 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Address at the opening of the Accra Assembly (two copies, one annotated), 1962 June 21 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Press release of 1963 May Day broadcast, 1963 May 3 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - "Oil for Ghana", 1963 September 28 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - "State Opening of Parliament", 1963 October 15 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - "Salute to Party Members", undated (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - "The Path," Kwame Nkrumah Revolutionary Guards, [1987] (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - "Political Africa," vol. 1, no. 6, 1970 June (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - The Post, no. 12, 1987 April (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Rural forum, vol.1, nos. 3, 7, 1986 May, Jun, 1987 July (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Sankofa, vol 1, nos. 2, 3 (one issue), 1977 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - "A Social Democratic Agenda for Ghana, the Philosophy of the National Democratic Congress", [2000] (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - The Spark, 1963 March 8 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - "Special Commemorative Brochure for the 25thAnniversary of Odeneho Oduro Numapau II (Essumejahene and Omanhene of Essumeja Traditional Area, 1975-2000)", 2000 October 20-24 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Talking Drums, vol. 1, no. 43, vol. 2, no.14, 1984 July 30, December 24, 31 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - The Verdict, vol.1, no. 1, 1985 August (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - "Voice of African Workers," Organization of African Trade Union Unity, 1978 Aug, Sep, Dec, 1979 Jan, [1985] (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - "White Paper on the Report of the Commission of Inquiry into the Yendi Disturbances of 25-27 March, 2002," Republic of Ghana, 2002 December 23 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Photographs, nine scenes from the Gold Coast, [1900] (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Photograph, Odumasi Agricultural Show, 1912 November (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Diagram of a train engine from the North British Locomotive Company, Glasgow, Circa 1950 (Box 1, Folder 31)
- Additional Material, 1945-2006; Accession 2010-M-069
  Arrangement
  Materials are arranged as received.
  - Printed material
    - Sankofa: Ghana's Illustrated Arts And Culture Magazine, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - The Verdict: Journal of The Revolutionary Organs, 1987, May-July (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Gold Coast Constitution, 1950 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Circulars issued by Judicial Adviser, Chief Commissioner and the Ashanti Judicial Adviser, 1945-1952 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Busia, Dr. K.A.
      - Letters to the chairman of the Assets Committee Ghana, 1972 May, 1977 January (Box 1, Folder 2)
      - Memorial service program, 1978 August (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Democracy Watch (Newsletter of the Ghana Center for Democratic Development), 2003 June (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - The Vision, 2004 May-2006 December (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Flamingo, 1966 June (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Welcome to Ghana tourist brochure, Undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - The Sunday Times Magazine (re Kwame Nkrumah), 1967 March (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Pension scheme comic advertisement, Undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Anti-Arthur Ankrah flyers, Undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Daily Graphic, 1966 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Ghanaian Times, 1966 February-1966 March (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Evening News, 1966 February (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Additional Material, 2002-2006; Accession 2011-M-084
  This accession comprises oversized posters published by the Department of Public Information Services, Accra, and arranged alphabetically by organization and/or title.
  - Electoral Commission of Ghana
    - District Assembly and Unit Committee Elections
      - "Don't Let Your Disability Disenfranchise You!", 2006 (Box 1)
      - "Let Us All Get Involved", 2006 (Box 1)
      - "Voting Steps at Polling Stations", 2006 (Box 1)
    - Presidential Election
      - "Notice of Poll: Presidential", 2004 December (Box 1)
        Poster includes names, photographs, party logos and affiliations of candidates nominated for presidency of Ghana in 2004.
  - "HIPC Benefit and other Projects", 2003 (Box 1)
    HIPC (Heavily Indebted Poor Countries) initiative was launched by the International Monetary Fund (IMF) and the World Bank in 1996 as an international response to provide debt relief to the neediest countries.
  - "Kufuor Commissions Projects", 2002 (Box 1)
    John Kofi Agyekum Kufuor was the second president of the Fourth Republic of Ghana (2001-2009).
  - "Kufuor's Historic Visit to Osudoku", 2002 (Box 1)
  - "Linking Up Communities", 2004 (Box 1)
  - "President's Special Initiative" (PSI), 2002 (Box 1)
  - "Progress in Education", 2004 (Box 1)
  - "Water for All", 2004 (Box 1)
- Additional material, 1961-2012; Accession 2015-M-001
  - Printed material, 1961-2012 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Posters, 2000-2012 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Oversize (Folder 3)
  - 2012 presidential election ephemera
    - Printed material: stickers, pocket calendar, registration forms, Progressive People's Party (PPP) platform statement, Polling Station Data Booklet (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Printed material for NPP Nana Akufo-Addo CD, Awurade Kae Nana, composed by Isaiah Kwadwo Ampong (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - New Patriotic Party (NPP) tote bag (Box 4)
    - Three shirts, NPP, Progressive People's Party (PPP), and National Democratic Congress (NDC) (Box 4)
    - Three fabric banners, NPP, NDC, and Convention People's Party (CPP) (Box 4)
    - Plasticized banner on roller, NPP (Box 4)
    - Small flag, NPP (Box 4)
    - Two baseball caps, NPP and NDC (Box 5)
    - Scarves, NPP (2) and NDC (2) (Box 6)
    - Headscarf, NPP (Box 6)
    - Key chains, NPP (2) and NDC (3) (Box 7)
    - Bracelets, NPP (2) and NDC (1) (Box 7)
    - Two wristlets, NPP and NDC (Box 7)
    - Two pins, NPP (Box 7)
    - Coaster, NPP (Box 7)
    - Small pennant, NPP (Box 7)
    - NPP Nana Akufo-Addo CD, Awurade Kae Nana, composed by Isaiah Kwadwo Ampong [commercially produced], 1 (Box 8)
      Conditions Governing Access
      Original audiovisual materials, as well as preservation and duplicating masters, may not be played. Researchers must consult use copies, or if none exist must pay for a use copy, which is retained by the repository. Researchers wishing to obtain an additional copy of non-commercially produced items for their personal use should consult the ordering reproductions information on the Manuscripts and Archives web site.